Yes, for the first time, welcome. There
is a WhatsApp group, there is a
Google Drive that will have all of
the shiurim and all of the folders
and all of the notes and everything
including chazarah notes later in this zman.
I apologize in advance for any jokes
that I say, any food that I
make fun of. Okay. So as I
mentioned this zman, we just finished zman
of basar b'chalav. So we're really just
continuing, which I think actually is good.
While the information is fresh and the
terms and the ideas and the lomdus
that we learned in the last zman
about basar b'chalav and ta'aroves and things
like that, chaticha na'ases neveila and things
like that, that is very very much
relevant for what we are going to
be doing this zman. So this zman
will take us through if you see
the, if you see in the booklet,
so you have siman tzadi hey which
we're going to do over the next
a number of weeks. Siman tzadi hey
is mostly focused on issues of nat
bar nat, which we'll talk about tonight,
נותן טעם בר נותן טעם. That's so
you can keep the regular. And then
you'll have to get a new Shulchan
Aruch for kuf kaf gimmel which we're
going to talk eventually about yayin nesech
and stam yeinam, yayin mevushal, you know
basically things that if you drink other
wines than just Moscato will affect you.
So in my house we'll be alright,
but maybe your house you'll have to
figure this out. So let's go if
you take the, open up the Shulchan
Aruch to siman tzadi hey and the
booklet to page number one. Let's review
something very quickly. We mentioned that the
Torah in three places says that you
cannot cook meat and milk together and
that teaches me three issurim. What are
those three issurim? Hana'ah, achilah, and bishul.
And bishul. That sounds like that sounds
right. There are three things the Halacha
tells us. Now we also learned that
when we create an issur of basar
b'chalav, that is because a ta'am is
created in the pot itself. So again,
I'll make it easy. There is going
to be a lot of terms over
the next few weeks that are very
like parve, dairy, eino ben yomo, so
you just have to like hold kop
as they say for a little bit.
But we mentioned that there's this idea
of nosein ta'am, okay? That means that
if I have a pot and I
make meatballs in that pot, within the
walls of the pot there is nesinas
ta'am, the pot, the meat gave flavor
into the walls of the pot. That
is true for the walls of a
pot, that is true for anything. If
you take a pot of meatballs and
you throw something parve in that pot
of meatballs and then you pull out
that parve thing, okay, you pull out
a potato, even though we did talk
about a Rema that maybe is meikel,
that if you cooked it together, there
is meat flavor in that potato. If
I ate that potato, what am I?
I am fleishig. Now if I take
a ben yomo pot, that means I
cooked this morning meatballs and I cleaned
it out then I cooked something else
in that pot, I cooked something parve
in that pot, could I eat those
noodles? Sure. Of course you could. Thank
you Eddie. Of course you could eat
those noodles, but would those noodles make
you fleishig? No. Could you eat those
noodles with milchig? That's what we're going
to discuss right now. We believe probably
not, but we are going to discuss
very relevant shaylos of what happened, I
just had this shayla in my house
erev pesach, erev the last days, no
sorry, erev Shabbos. One of my boys
was making something and he tasted an
onion that was cut up with a
fleishig knife. And there was a shayla
of now he wants to eat something
milchig. So I told him he'd better
call somebody else. Okay. So the Gemara
in Chullin, the Gemara the first source,
the Gemara in Chullin tells us the
following. The Gemara, we learned this Gemara
last time, but now we didn't spend
as much time on nat bar nat
or נתינת טעם בר נתינת טעם. But
let's go. The following: itmar, דגים שעלו
בקערה. So the Gemara tells us that
if I had fish, okay if I
had fish, let's take one step back.
Just to flush out the rest of
this, there is nesinas ta'am, but after
twenty-four hours we call that nosein ta'am
lifgam. That means that after twenty-four hours,
I'm not as concerned anymore because whatever
flavor is actually there is no longer
a positive flavor but is a negative
flavor. It's going to make the taste
bad. We focus on ta'am. So if
I made meatballs in a fleishig pot
and twenty-eight hours later I made something
in that same pot, I made something
milchig even in that pot, we would
say what's the status of the food?
You could eat it. It's nesinas ta'am,
it's nosein. Now if you didn't clean
it, it's gross. That would be an
issue. But nosein ta'am lifgam means after
twenty-four hours, that's when we're definitely more
lenient. So the first shayla the rabbi's
going to ask when you call, the
first shayla's going to be, was it
cold? Then it's going to be, when
was the last time the thing was
used? So now let's get into this
concept. So the Gemara... The Gemara tells
us that a machlokes between Rav and
Shmuel regarding the status of hot pareve
fish, okay, דגים שעלו בקערה. That means
I cooked fish. רב אמר אסור לאכלן
בכותח. So Rav says you can't, that
fish cannot be eaten with dairy. Why
not? What is the reason according to
Rav? Because there is no way that
well here the k'arah is a fleishig
ben yomo. So according to Rav why
can't I eat that fish with dairy
with milchig? Because the fish absorbed taam
from the meat. It was a ben
yomo. I made meatballs in the morning,
I cleaned it out, I made fish
later in the afternoon, completely pareve fish,
but the taam of the meatballs is
still in the walls of the pot
and there that when I heat it
up the taam comes into the fish,
the fish is now fleishig. Why would
that be a question? Hold on a
sec, hold on a sec, hold on
a sec. שמואל אמר מותר לאכלן בכותח.
Shmuel says you can eat it with
the some kutach is a dairy kind
of thing you could eat it with
that because רב אמר נותן טעם הוא.
Rav says it's noten taam. What do
you mean? The meat was noten taam
from the wall into the fish. Shmuel
amar muttar because נותן טעם בר נותן
טעם הוא. There's a concept called for
the rest of the zman we're going
to call it nat bar nat, not
נותן טעם בר נותן טעם. You know
for example in the Gemara the Gemara
is in Gittin, we're learning Gittin in
the yeshiva this year. So the Gemara
in Gittin the first eight blatt is
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. When you sign
a get you have to say בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם but you learn Gittin
no one ever says בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם you say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם.
You say like that. Say very fast.
So we told our seniors when the
Roshei Yeshiva come to interview you for
the yeshivas and they say what are
you learning in Gittin they don't say
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם you have to
speed through it so you know it
sounds like you know what you're talking
about, okay? So nat bar nat, okay?
They do know what they're talking about
but it's always good to help them.
Okay? There's a concept called nat bar
nat. Nat bar nat means according to
Shmuel the meatballs were noten taam into
the walls of the pot. The walls
of the pot are noten taam into
the fish. That is a very very
weak taste. That is not strong enough
and נותן טעם בר נותן טעם we
think is according to Shmuel which the
Gemara paskens like is going to be
okay. The Gemara the Tosafos in Zevachim
in source number two explains that we
saw a little bit of this Tosafos.
Says the Tosafos in Zevachim ואם לא
הביא ראיה לדבריו מקדירה שבישלו בה בשר
לא יבשלו בה חלב בשביל דנותן טעם
when I if I cooked meat, don't
cook in it milk because it's noten
taam. דהתם לאו נותן טעם בר נותן
טעם הוא that's not נותן טעם בר
נותן טעם שפעמים שהטעם השני באיסור דהיינו
בשר וחלב sometimes the second taste is
in a prohibition namely basar vechalav takes
effect when the meat and the milk
are fused together okay like when I
cook milk in a fleishig pot that's
an issue אבל כאן הטעם השני בהיתר
וקודם שיבא לידי איסור נתבטל הטעם בדגים
לפי שהוא שני meaning when the fish
is muttar by itself the meatballs are
muttar by themselves so what happens? I
have two muttar items in that situation
I didn't fuse any issur together. When
I made mamash basar vechalav and I
created an entity a cheftza shel issur
that's a problem and that's going to
be noten taam. But you're telling me
according to Shmuel I have fish the
fish is pareve. The meat's fleishig. They're
both noten taam into other things by
the time they meet together it's a
weak noten taam and therefore we do
not imply that it's already inherently forbidden
and noten taam is going to be
okay. Halacha lemaaseh this how we pasken
if you look in the Beis Yosef.
Says the Beis Yosef in source number
three. The Beis Yosef says you're right
we pasken like Shmuel nat bar nat
not a problem. However says the Beis
Yosef it is a three way machlokes
how to understand what it means דגים
שעלו בקערה. So before we even see
these three Rishonim, the Rivan, the Sefer
HaTerumah, and the Rambam and there's a
fourth what does it sound like? I
gave you a lot of information I
said that דגים שעלו בקערה fish that
is in a plate is fish that
was cooked in a fish cooked in
a ben yomo fleishig pot. What does
it sound like דגים שעלו בקערה? It
was no water. Otherwise it was touching.
So where was the fish was cooked
where? Up against the metal. Some fish.
Right. It doesn't even sound like... so
okay that's a machlokes. It could be
that it was cooked in that pot
or it could be as Joel is
saying it was cooked in another pot
and then it came onto a pot
maybe that is fleishig. So let's see
three machlokes Rishonim. So the Rivan chosno
the father in law of the Rivan
was. The *Rivan chasno*, *Rashi*, *kasav mishmo*,
אלו אין נתבשלו לו. Says the *Rivan*
that *Shmuel* only allows eating the fish
when the, okay, again, eating the fish
with *milkchik* when the hot fish was
placed on a *fleishig* dish. Okay, אף
על גב דבאלו נמי קבלו כדי קליפה,
טעמן בשר בבליעה מועטת התיר נותן טעם
בר נותן טעם. אבל נתבשלו ונבלעו כל
טעם הבשר שבלוע בקדירה, but if you're
telling me that I *mamish* did what?
I cooked the fish in that *fleishig
ben yomo* pot, *asur le'ochlo bekutach*. According
to, good, the *Rivan*, *Rashi*, and *Rabbi*
Doug say the following: if you cook
fish in a *fleishig* pot, that is
not, that is not נותן טעם בר
נותן טעם. That is *mamish* cooking it
and therefore the only time that *Shmuel*
really held that it's okay is when
I cooked it by, I cooked the
fish, I took the fish that was
cooked in a *parve* pot, on a
whatever pot, it doesn't matter, and then
I took that fish and I put
it on a *ben yomo fleishig* plate.
Okay, that's נותן טעם בר נותן טעם.
Why? Because the meat, the whatever, the
meatballs were the *nosein ta'am*, then I
took it onto the plate, that plate's
not a real *fleishig* plate, the *fleishig*
plate is a נותן טעם בר נותן
טעם plate, it's a *nab bar nab*
plate. What? We're gonna talk, we're gonna
talk about all those things in a
second. Okay, so says the *Rivan* in
the name of *Rashi*, that's the only
time he's going to be *meikel*. In
comes the *Sefer HaTruma* and the *Rosh*
and others and the *Tur*, וכתב הראש
וספר התרומה the other way, התיר ירקות
וקטניות שנתבשלו בקדירה בת יומא חלבת, the
other way around. They allow the fish
that was cooked in a *fleishig ben
yomo* pot to be eaten with *milkchik*,
רק שמנקה מחלב לאכל בתבשיל של בשר,
so long as obviously it's been cleaned
out, because they believe אפילו נאמר אלו
אין נצלו לו כשנתבשלו שרי, משום דאיכא
שלשה נותן טעם. They actually say it
was weakened three times. Forget *nosein ta'am*,
forget *nat bar nat*, actually weakened, one
sec, hold on, hold on, *nat bar
nat* to the third degree. The meat
to the pot is one, what's next?
The pot קדירה במים והמים בירק. So
don't view the water as everything. I
cooked meatballs this morning, meatballs went into
my pot. That is *nosein ta'am* one.
The meatballs went into the water, *nosein
ta'am* two. The water was *nosein ta'am*
into the fish, that's crazy. That's נותן
טעם בר נותן טעם בר נותן טעם,
that's *mutar*. That's what's the logic though,
that the water cooks before the item
in the water? Yes, because you need
a medium to transfer heat. I need
a medium to transfer *ta'am*. We don't,
it's not just a magic potion, something
has to transfer heat, transfer the taste.
So the water transfers the taste, but
it doesn't happen at the same time.
The water absorbs from the thing and
then it puts it in, it's floating
in the pot, so the water is,
is being is transferred even if it
happens in a split second. But the
*Tur*, the *Sefer HaTruma*, and the *Rosh*
say that's enough and therefore if I
made meatballs this morning and I cooked
fish this afternoon, do not leave here
before we do *halacha lema'aseh* and go
home, but according to the *Tur* and
the *Rosh* and the *Sefer HaTruma* I
could go ahead and eat that fish
with whatever *milkchik* you wanted to eat
it with. Hold on, hold on, hold
on, hold on, there's a lot of
details. I want to get through a
number more *mekomos* unless it's I don't
understand what that source was, because that's
fine, but according to the *Rosh*, how
you're translating this, he says the *yerakos*
that were cooked in a *ben yomo
chalavas*. *Chalavas*? Where are you getting this
was cooked in a *fleishig* pot to
start with? The fish was cooked in
the *Rosh* pot. But the vegetables, *yerakos*,
*ben yomos*, *shenisbashlu bak*... He's saying the
other way I just said the other
way around. If I cooked it in
a *milkchik* pot it's a *fleishig*, other
just do the other way around. If
I cooked them all in a, he
says, if I cooked it all in
a *bas yoma chalavas*, as long as
it's clean, I could, if I later
cooked something *betavshil shel basar* I can
eat it. I made macaroni and cheese
this morning, I cleaned it out, I
made something *fleishig* in there, I can
eat it together, I can eat it.
Meaning whatever is as long as it's
been cleaned out, whatever I put in
that pot afterwards doesn't have the status
of what it was this morning. No,
no, then he continues in the underline,
he continues in the underline, חלב בקדירה
קדירה במים ומים בירק, even though if
it's it's. 24 hours? That's what he's
saying, yeah. According to the Rashi he's
talking about boiling vegetables, but he equates
boiling vegetables where you have a full
pot of a liquid medium as opposed
to if you were frying a piece
of meat that had lachluchit on it.
So we're talking about that, potentially but
depends on how much oil you have.
Yeah, that might, that might be. We're
going to talk about that. And then
he quotes the third is the Rambam.
וכן נראה דעת הרמבם. Then he quotes
the Rambam to, you know, just like
to your point, שכתבו בפרק ט מהלכות
מאכלות אסורות, קערה שאכלו בה בשר, if
I have a plate that I was
eating meat, ובשלו בה דגים אותם דגים
מותר לאוכלן בכותח. So according to the
Rambam, he says ולא חילק בין צליה
לבישול כלל. According to the Rambam, even
if the fish I allowed, I can
eat the fish with dairy if it
was cooked in a fleishig ben yomo
pot, even if it was fried. Again
because of nat bar nat. He quotes
here in the footnote, by the way,
a comment of the Issur v'Hetter that
you can eat it like the Rivash,
a little bit of like a, we'll
call it a fourth opinion or a
three-eighths, or B, but anyway, these are
the three opinions. So according to the
Rambam, the plate, it says אכלו בה
בשר ובשלו בה דגים. So is he
saying that you cooked meat in that,
but it says אכלו? That's not just
you cooked? Yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah, we'll
see, we'll see a little bit later
in the Rema about plates and stuff
like that. Okay. So now go to
the Shulchan Aruch in Tzadi-Hei. Is this
davar charif? A little bit later. Yeah,
a little bit, a little bit. Okay,
so if you go into Siman Tzadi-Hei
the following. Shulchan Aruch in Seif Aleph
says דגים שנתבשלו או שנתצלו בקדירה של
בשר. The fish that I cooked in
a meat, in a meat pot. rechuza
yafeh. All I gotta do is clean
it out really, really well. Right? If
I clean it out really, really well
שאין שום שומן דבוק בה. As long
as there's really nothing that's left there,
then mutar l'ochlan b'kutach. Right? Like the
Rambam, I can eat it with the
dairy thing. Why? Exactly as we just
said. משום דהוי נותן טעם בר נותן
טעם דהיתרא. It's why d'heteira? Because there
is נט בר נט דאיסורא. Right? Certain
things that become an issur just because
the ta'am is weakened doesn't matter. If
I took treifus tonight and cooked it
in my pot and then I said,
\"Oh, I cooked treifus in this morning
and now I had other treifus\". I
don't care that you have other treifus
in there. I don't care that it's
later. I don't care that you cleaned
it out. It's treifus. Treifus is an
issur no matter what. Doesn't matter. But
נותן טעם בר נותן טעם דהיתרא of
meat in a pot and milk in
a pot that later are because of
נותן טעם בר נותן טעם joined together,
that's what we're talking about. ואם לא
היה רחוצה יפה, and if you didn't
wash it out so nicely, אם יש
ממש על פני הקדירה יוצא ממנו בשישים
מהדגים אסור לאוכלן בכותח. All right, then
you have to figure out if you
had shishim or not. Okay, exactly we
just saw in the Gemara and then
in the Rambam. Seif Beis. Okay, now
the Shulchan Aruch is going to clarify
what exactly is this halacha of nat
bar nat. So let's follow. ביצה שנתבשלה
במים בקדירה חולבת. I take an egg,
okay, and I cooked it in a
milchig pot. I want to take that
egg. An egg is parve or fleishig?
Parve. There we go. מותר לתת אותה
בתוך התרנגולת. If you're thinking, \"What does
that mean?\" That is exactly what that
sounds like. It's Thanksgiving morning and you
take that egg and you shove it
in the turkey. Afilu l'chatchila says the,
now why? All right, now I took
the, I had a milchig pot. ביצה
שנתבשלה במים בקדירה חולבת, a milchig pot.
I cooked an egg in a milchig
pot. I could stick that egg in
a turkey, or hen, chicken, whichever you
like. Afilu l'chatchila I could even do
it l'chatchila. Why is that okay? Because
אבל אם נתבשלה בקדירה עם בשר, that's
different. If I had a milchig pot,
that means that maybe this morning I
made macaroni and cheese. I cleaned it
out. It is a milchig pot. For
the next 24 hours that pot is
a milchig pot. But when I cooked
the eggs alone, what was milchig inside
the pot? Nothing. The only thing that
was milchig inside the pot was the
ta'am from this morning of the macaroni
and cheese that was back into, but
the egg isn't a milchig egg. So
if I took that egg and I
put it in a turkey, that's not
going to do anything, that's not a
problem. But if I had meat sauce
and I threw an egg in there,
and then I took that egg, right,
and I took that egg, that, I'm
sorry, what's a macaroni and cheese and
I took that egg, that egg is
now what? Milchig. נתבשלה בקדירה עם בשר.
He says it by the meat. But
if the parve item is cooked together
with meat, afilu b'klippa... Asur le'ochlo bechutach.
Okay, an egg cooked with meat or
cooked with dairy could not be eaten,
you can't use it for the other
one. Okay. Good. Fershteis? Veiter. Says the
Rema: Veyesh machmirim. So the Rema says,
there are those that are machmir בצליה
ובשול לאסור נותן טעם בר נותן טעם.
Oh, so close. Says the Rema, like
the Rivan, quoting Rashi, and the Aruch,
and the Mordechai, there are those that
are machmir even if it's נותן טעם
בר נותן טעם, even if it's not
bar nat, to be machmir not to
use it. The Rema says, let's continue,
right? The Rema actually a little bit
later, we'll put him back to that
Issur Veheter, but let's continue. Vehaminhag le'asor
lechatchila, and the Rema says, and the
minhag is to be to assur this.
That means that what? The fish that
was cooked in a fleishig ben yomo
pot, not with fleishig, a fleishig ben
yomo pot, that fish the Rema says
lechatchila should not be eaten together with
dairy. Okay. What about bedieved? Excellent. We're
going to come back to that next
time. Okay. But this is how the
Rema paskens. So, but ובדיעבד מותר בכל
ענין דדוקא לאכלם עם חלב ובשר עצמו.
The Rema says, but if dairy was
added to it, meaning I made, I
made meatballs in the morning, I cleaned
it out, I have, I made fish
in there in the afternoon, I didn't
realize the pot was, I took the
fish and I, I added milk and
I add all this other stuff, says
the Rema, you could eat that fish.
You could eat that fish. The shaila
we're going to talk about soon is
can I do that lechatchila? Okay. We
have the shaila, we have the shaila
a lot. The shaila comes up a
lot. I'm running out of pots. It's
Friday afternoon. I only have a milchig
pot. Can I use, these are going
to come up. So the Rema says,
bedieved it's going to be mutar. Meaning,
in essence, why does the Rema say
that? Let's understand how the Rema comes
to this. The Rema's not, if it's
mutar it's mutar, if it's assur it's
assur. The Rema says, yes, really we
don't, we don't in essence pasken like
the Rivan. I, we pasken like how
the Shulchan Aruch paskens, like the Rambam,
that it's nosein ta'am it's not bar
nat. However, we're going to be machmir
about it, but in any situation it's
a, this is a good reminder of
what machmir generally means. Machmir is a
good thing. Machmir is not a bad
thing. Machmir is not a person who's
a religious fanatic. A chumra means there
is basis in halacha for such a
thing. Right? So the Rema says, this
is what it means to be machmir.
Yes, the Rivan, yes, the Shulchan Aruch
says this, we follow the Rivan. However,
in cases of need, a bedieved, it's
mutar because it's only a chumra. Right?
A person who keeps 72 minutes after
Shabbos is a chumra, right? That's the
Rabbeinu Tam, and in case of need
if they keep it as a chumra,
they're able to be meikel on certain
things because it's a chumra. Okay. Fine.
That's the Rema. Okay. Yeah. The Rema
adds, okay, so now if you look
ואפילו אם ליתן בה כלי שלהם מותר
לכתחילה. Okay. Vechein nahagu. So we pasken
like this. This is how we pasken
as Ashkenazim. This is how we pasken.
Then the Rema begins to add four
different halachos. We're going to talk about
a few of them right now. So
let's go one by one. Okay. He
says first, וכן אם לא נתבשלו או
נצלו תחילה. Let's say that I actually
didn't cook them at all together. Rather
what did I do? רק עלו בכלי
של בשר מותר לאכלן עם חלב עצמו
וכן להיפך. Fish cooked in a ben
yomo pot, okay, in a fleishig ben
yomo pot, got that? Fish cooked in
a fleishig ben yomo pot can be
put lechatchila on a dairy ben yomo
plate. Okay? Clean plate, not like full
of yogurt. Okay? Next. That's number one.
I'll tell you where the shaila comes
up. Shaila comes up that a person
makes pasta in a fleishig ben yomo
pot. Okay? They make pasta in a
fleishig ben yomo pot and they want
to know if they could add cheese
or not to it. Shulchan Aruch would
say yes. The Rema would say no.
That's how we pasken. That's how we
pasken. That the noodles aren't, the spaghetti
will not make you fleishig, you cannot
eat that spaghetti. If you by accident
did it and you didn't realize, the
Rema would say it's fine. Okay? That's
number one. But what would the Rema
say if it was an eino ben
yomo pot? I made... I'm just telling
you, do not share this halacha in
your house. You will get yelled at.
Okay? This is a regular halacha, it's
the Rema paskins, I could take the.
The reason is you find this in
a lot of the in the Rishonim,
that's why we have multiple sets of
pots. If yes, you could have one
pot and every other day make something
in it, it gets confusing. But if
you had an eino ben yomo fleishig
pot, you made spaghetti in there and
you wanted to add cheese lechatchila the
Rema would say go ahead. Okay? You'd
feel weird doing it. You took that
pot that it came out of the
fleishig dishwasher and then you'd feel weird
doing it, but that's how the Rema
paskins. Next. היה הכלי שנתבשלו או נצלו
בו לפגם. Before we get to the
second halacha, okay, go to the source
for one second to source number four
to the Bedek HaBayis. Say the question
is as we just mentioned can I
do this or not lechatchila? Just I
know we said this outside but let's
look at it inside. Bedek HaBayis is
Rabbi Yosef Karo. So if I made
vegetables שנתבשלו בקדרה חולבת אפילו בת יומא,
even if it's that day, מותר לאכלו
בתבשיל של בשר, ונראה דדוקא בדיעבד אבל
לכתחילה אין לו לבשל בכלי של חלב.
So the Bedek HaBayis quotes, here it's
actually quoting the Rabbeinu Yerucham, that actually
the Rabbeinu Yerucham says no, you shouldn't
do it lechatchila, bedieved like the Rema
says. Says the Bedek HaBayis, says Rabbi
Yosef Karo, ein devarav nirim. No. לכתחילה
נמי מותר לבשל בכלי של חלב. That's
fine. You could do it even like
we just said, it would be fine
to intentionally do this kind of thing.
That's how the Sephardim might give a
psak. We obviously do not follow that
psak. If you turn the page, because
from the language of the Shulchan Aruch
it sounds like shenisbashlu or shenitzlu. It
sounds like they already did it. Can
I do it lechatchila? So here you
have in Halichot Olam, Rav Ovadia. So
Rav Ovadia writes ולא עוד אלא אפילו
הוא יודע מראש. I know, says Rav
Ovadia. I am cooking with intention that
later I'm going to eat this with
dairy, that's fine. שעתיד לעשות לבן או
חמאה באורז מותר לבשל האורז בקדירה בשר
בת יומא. Says Rabbi Yosef Karo, I
took a pot, it's a fleishig pot,
it's ben yomo, and it's clean. I'm
going to cook rice in there and
later I am going to eat that
rice with butter. Says Rav Ovadia, that
is going to be okay. Even cooking
it lechatchila to do it is going
to be okay. That's what I mean.
But the Rema's lechatchila is that adding
the cheese lechatchila? Yeah. No, or cooking,
meaning is the lechatchila or the Rema
says it's a problem is you when
you decide to cook it in the
fleishig pot or when you decide to
put the cheese on? So no, so
the Rema says we don't do it.
Rema says we don't do it. But
I'm saying what where are we measuring?
Oh, if you want to eat a
pareve, no one's going to care. No,
no, I'm saying you cooked in the
fleishig pot. That's fine. No, and then
you want to add cheese on. That's
the lechatchila. For the Rema, that's a
problem still. For the Rema it's a
problem. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, so that's
how the Rav Ovadia paskins. If you
look in, okay so let's go now
to source number six to the Badai
HaShulchan, Shagapo Cohen? 508? The great Sephardic
that he put out all on Yoreh
Deah. So he says the following. He
says the opinion of the Rema, he
quotes the Gra. Ube'er HaGra da'ato. This
we're going to see a machlokes here,
a very, very fundamental machlokes right now,
the Gra in this source and the
Chachmat Adam in the next source. Okay.
So by the opinion of the Rema,
which we just said we don't do
this, we don't cook there lechatchila, באר
הגר''א דעתו דמותר אף לכתחילה. He quotes
the Gra that says the Rema allows
cooking pareve food in only an eino
ben yomo pot. Okay? That's okay lechatchila.
That means that if I have a
pot over twenty-four hours and I want
to use it, that would be okay
lechatchila. ואף בקדירה אין אסור לכתחילה שאינו
בן יומא אלא משום גזירה אטו בן
יומא. Okay, so okay, a gezeira atu.
We have this concept a lot of
times, we have a gezeira atu, which
means we're doing this because we don't
want you to come to do something
else, right? We don't want you to
come to cook in a ben yomo
and therefore we asser in eino ben
yomo. But an eino ben yomo by
itself is not really going to be
a problem. But he continues מה שאין
כן כאן. However, דאף בן יומו מותר
מדינא כנזכר לעיל. However, a ben yomo
pot really he says should be allowed
if you cooked pareve. Meaning Chazal are
concerned that I might come to use
a ben yomo pot. You're not going
to cook in it? So what the
Gra is saying is that even if
I cook pareve... I cooked *pareve* in
a dairy *Ben yomo* pot. Okay, I
cooked *pareve* in a dairy *Ben yomo*
pot, the *Rama* really holds that that's
okay. Okay, if I cooked dairy in
a *pareve Ben yomo* pot, that would
be okay to eat it with something
else because that's really how he holds.
And he continues and he says in
the underline: חזינן דבדיעבד מותר בזה רק
לכתחילה נוהגים להחמיר. This whole thing that
we just mentioned that on *lechatchila* we're
*machmir*, אין חומרא זו אלא בבן יומו.
That's when it comes to a *Ben
yomo*. אבל באינו בן יומו הדרינן לעיקר
הדין דנת בר נת שרי אף בישול
לכתחילה באינו בן יומו מותר אף לכתחילה.
What the *Gra* holds is that the
whole this whole thing is only about
a *Ben yomo*. I don't want you
to use a *Ben yomo* and therefore
we're going to be *machmir*. But if
I use an *eino Ben yomo* even
with intention to do it with the
other food, the *Rama* would say not
a problem. So if I had an
*eino Ben yomo* pot and I cooked
spaghetti in that *eino Ben yomo* pot,
it doesn't matter. I cook fish, doesn't
matter. Even *lechatchila* if I called it
a *fleishig eino Ben yomo* pot, that
means I made meatballs thirty-six hours ago,
I take it out tonight, I make
fish and I know I'm going to
eat that fish with dairy, the *Rama*
according to the *Gra* says it's not
a problem. The *Chazal* were not *machmir*
about that, that's not *gezeira atu*, we're
only *gezeira atu* a *Ben yomo*. Okay,
the *Chachmas Adam* argues. *Chachmas Adam* argues
and he says the *Rama* only allows
eating fish with dairy if it was
already cooked in an *eino Ben yomo*
pot, but not *lechatchila*. And he says:
אם היה הכלי שנתבשל בו אינו בן
יומו. If I have a *kli* that
I cooked in that was an *eino
Ben yomo*, okay, מותר לאכלו בחלב אפילו
לדידן אבל אסור לכתחילה. Says the *Chachmas
Adam*, I can't do it *lechatchila*, לבשל
בכלי שאינו בן יומו כדי לאכלו בחלב,
okay, because that's *assur lechatchila*. The *noten
ta'am lifgam assur lechatchila*. What does that
mean? Means like this: so this is
a very, very fundamental *machlokes*, *Gra* and
*Chachmas Adam*. If we follow the *Gra*
we'd be in a better spot, but
we actually don't in this situation, we
follow the *Chachmas Adam*. The *Chachmas Adam*
says again if I took an *eino
Ben yomo fleishig* pot and I made
fish and then by accident I mixed
milk into it, totally fine. The *Chachmas
Adam* says but to take an *eino
Ben yomo fleishig* pot, cook spaghetti in
there with the intention that I'm going
to melt cheese onto those spaghetti noodles,
says the *Chachmas Adam*, that's *assur*. Why?
Because even though you're going to throw
at me *noten ta'am lifgam*, that's all
good and dandy if it was by
accident. But this is *lechatchila*. We don't
do it *lechatchila*. I don't utilize anything
*lechatchila* when it's an *issur*. So says
the *Chachmas Adam*, we are therefore *machmir*.
Most of the modern day *poskim* including
Rav Elyashiv and including if you look
in the *kashrus* books, follow this *Chachmas
Adam*. So therefore, you can't really have
one pot in your house. Because that
one pot is always going to be
an *eino Ben yomo* of something. *Lechatchila*...
*bediavad* it would be okay. Or maybe
*bediavad* means I only have one pot,
but to rely that I'm going to
use it to make pasta to eat
with cheese when it was *fleishig* thirty-six
hours ago, that we're *machmir* about. Okay.
But the *Chachmas Adam's* whole point is
saying for *lechatchila* here is still to
say *eino Ben yomo*. It's to cook
it with intention to use. Correct. Add
cheese if you... No, you could cooking's
never a problem. No no no, I'm
saying there's diff... No, one second. But
if I have a thirty-six hour pot,
okay? I'm gonna make... it was *fleishig*
yesterday morning. Tonight, I'm gonna make spaghetti
in this pot and I know that
afterwards I'm gonna put cheese in. Right,
that's *lechatchila* for sure. Right, but I
can make spaghetti in that pot, it's
not a problem. No but if I
already... let's say I make spaghetti in
this *eino Ben yomo* pot yesterday and
today I decide I want to put
cheese on. Is that *lechatchila* or *bediavad*?
So that seems to be okay, correct.
Meaning, if I... now you can't you
can't *harama* it, yeah yeah. I don't
know what I want to make it
for and your whole fridge is full
of cheese. Yeah yeah, correct, correct. Doesn't...
I don't have to know my intention
but as long as my intention is
not to do that thing, so long
that that would be okay. Now if
a person's like, well I didn't really
know what I wanted yesterday. Right. Okay,
but that's the point because you're not
creating an *issur*. Right. You're cooking *pareve*
pasta. That's fine. But if your intention
was that I'm going to cook it
and then put cheese to it so
it's a problem. They have in the
in the notes I'll send that later
a whole chart of everything that you
can go over and you can review,
it's really wonderful and amazing for... you
can look at that on your own.
Okay. So a few examples. You go
to source number eight. Okay. So we
just mentioned the Rema paskens that parve
food in an eino ben yomo pot
could be eaten with fleishig. There's a
machlokes could I do it lechatchila? So
they quote here something very fascinating. So
in many many kosher ice cream places,
they make both lines of parve and
dairy, they're not necessarily like, they could
be on the same line. So you
look in Dayan Weiss, the Minchas Yitzchak,
they're making parve ice cream in eino
ben yomo dairy utensils. Okay? It's an
eino ben yomo dairy pot and they're
calling that ice cream parve. So Dayan
Weiss, Dayan Weiss was one of the
great great poskim in Eretz Yisrael, was
the dayan of the Edah Hachareidis and
the Bedatz, massive massive talmid chacham. So
it says Dayan Weiss: מה שנשאלתי בענין
גלידה פרוה שנעשה שביום שלפניו נעשה באותו
כלי גלידה חלבי yesterday or it just
means eino ben yomo, it was in
a milchig pot. ואוכלים אותה עם בשר.
Now, did they really eat it with
meat? Not but they're calling it parve.
If I call something parve, I could
eat it with meat. והעליתי שם לאסור
לעשות כן לכתחילה. And I thought that
this should be assur, right? Because when
you label it parve, that's implying that
if something is parve, it could be
eaten with parve or meat or dairy,
'cause it's parve. He's- he don't hold
anything yet. וכתבתי לדחות הצד להיתר. So
he says ובנידון דהוי נט בר נט
כתבתי וזה הלשון אחר מעת לעת אבד
כחו יפה ונותן טעם לפגם מכל מקום
יש להחמיר לכתחילה. How- it doesn't matter.
Even if you clean it well, that-
that we should be machmir. The Rema
does not really allow us to do
that. If you go to the next
source though- There's no cooking involved. Right,
there's no- there's no heat involved in
making ice cream. So how is it
right or wrong? There's cold. Right, it's
all cold. It's all cold ingredients. I
have no idea. I'm just going to
trust Dayan Weiss. I don't- Okay, so
in other words he's- I get it,
I don't know. I don't know. I
don't know. In other words, he's holding
that that should be labeled not parve
but dairy equipment. We're not at dairy
equipment yet. Not dairy equipment. Hold on.
He's saying that you can't use- that's
a good question, I don't know. I'd
have to find that. But the Ohel
Yaakov here, they quote the following: that
actually don't because what do most people
make- make ice cream for? Dessert. Dessert
is not usually, even if you're a
big meat guy, you don't have meat
for dessert. So when you make it,
says the Ohel Yaakov, גלידה נאכלת ברוב
העולם לקינוח for dessert, שהיו אוכלים לבד
ולכן כשבעלת הבית עושה גלידה נעשה על
דעת they're not making it like, no,
they're making it for parve and therefore
everything is going to be okay. This
leads us to a very common shaila
in source number ten. If I baked
a parve cake, okay, a chocolate cake
for dessert in an eino ben yomo
fleishig pan. This is a very common
shaila. I didn't, right? Most people will
have parve dishes or parve baking sheets,
but I didn't use it. I used
a fleishig eino ben yomo fleishig pan.
And now, so again, I had meatballs,
I made in my pot, Wednesday morning.
Wednesday morning I made meatballs. Thursday night
I make a chocolate cake. I have
that chocolate cake, I finish Shabbos and
now it's Sunday morning and I have
a coffee and I want to know,
could I eat that cake some of
that cake with the coffee? To not
real coffee because we're talking about milchig
coffee here with cream, like normal people.
Good. Let's get back to that zman.
Okay. Says the Megillas Sefer the following:
וכן נראה שמותר לבשל שוקולד וכיוצא בזה
בסיר בשרי שאינו בן יומו כדי לעשותם
בעוגה אף שאוכלים עם כוס קפה שיש
בו חלב. That would be okay. Why
would that be okay? shelo naaseh and
Jules, this gets back to your point,
להדיא רק בשביל זה. This goes even
further. When I made my chocolate cake,
unless you really made it, I'm going
to make this for Sunday morning, if
you want a piece of it on
Shabbos go ahead but that's my- that's
my coffee cake. You're making it dessert
for Shabbos. That's your intention. You don't
have to start like figuring out every
scenario and every like- you made it
for Shabbos, dessert for Shabbos. If you
end up wanting it on Sunday morning,
okay, so that's Sunday morning and therefore
it would be okay. This leads us
to the whole discussion about DE and
things like that. I'm going to leave
it to you, you can read it
partially in the notes. But I'm going
to skip it 'cause you can read
it for you but I do want
to point one thing out and we'll-
we'll end with this. A very common...
A very common misconception when it comes
to DE and these kind of things
which, okay, the OU stopped doing DE
a long time ago. Okay? Either it
got confusing, Kashrus organizations, they, I'm sorry,
the companies didn't like it, they wanted
it to be uniform and what was
actually on like, they didn't like it.
DE or not DE. Still used for
a few things. So all of that,
all of that, all of that. Let
me just give me this, we'll do
Ma'ariv and then everybody, we could talk
afterwards. There are certain things that like,
like Oreos, there are certain things that
are, you know, DE, should always check
back with the OU. I know somebody
who's like always so nervous because the
OU says you should check back in
and every like six months he's always
like, I don't know, maybe they changed
it again, so he wouldn't eat them.
Like Oreos are DE and things like
that, right? There are certain things that
you can look at the ingredients and
you can say, oh, there's no, there's
no milk in there. Bederech klal, that
is not a way. There are certain
things, I think if there's no like,
no concern of allergy for milk. Looking
at ingredients, I tell my students all
the time, looking at ingredients does you
nothing because what we require as what
makes something milchig or not is not
only the line in which it was
produced and the heat and the ben
yomo and eino ben yomo. There are
certain things that the FDA says that
is so little milk you don't have
to call that dairy. We don't consider
that so little milk. So sometimes a
product might say contains dairy, it's dairy-free.
It's not what we, and it says
OUD. So some people are like, ah,
there's no way it's OUD, I looked
in the ingredients, there must be DE.
It's not DE. Sometimes, sometimes things are
DE, you've got to call the OU
because email Webby Rabbi, Rabbi Webby at
ou.org. And sometimes, I mentioned this last
month, there were these, there are parve
ice cream brands that have OUD. Talenti
was one of them. It says OUD,
but it says dairy-free. People were mamash
eating it after, after Shabbos meals. It's
mamash milchig. It has milk in it.
Ah, it says dairy-free? Yeah, because the
FDA says that so little milk you
don't require it, but that doesn't mean,
forgetting ben yomo and eino ben yomo,
it doesn't necessarily mean that something's always
dairy-free. We'll pick it up again next
week.